software engineering radio episode 22
listener feedback
hi everybody welcome to another episode
of software engineering radio this is
another listener feedback episode so
first of all thanks to all of you for
giving us feedback in general and also
to the specific questions we've asked
you to give us feedback to it's really
quite cool to to get such positive
feedback on on work on the work we're
doing and it really motivates us to
continue with a podcast specifically we
had been asking you to give us feedback
with regards to our hands-on episode on
model demand software development which
was episode 16 so the question we raised
was whether it makes sense to have a
podcast where we expect you to take a
look at source code as we speak and your
feedback was overwhelmingly positive in
two respects
first of all it was positive in the
sense that you said that it's really
great to have an hands-on podcast and
that looking at the source code actually
really helped and that this kind of
practice oriented material is really
useful the other question we raised was
whether it makes sense to listen to the
podcast without actually looking at the
source code because you might be on the
train or in the car and also there the
feedback was overwhelmingly positive in
the sense that yes it makes sense to
only listen to it the source code is
useful but not really necessary
so we'll certainly produce additional
hands-on episodes in the future although
the next couple of episodes because
they've been in the pipeline for a while
aren't hands-on episodes there were also
some more specific suggestions on how to
improve such hands-on episodes one was
that we could think about producing a
video podcast and actually filming or
screen capturing what we do on the
screen and yes
yes we could do that but you know
producing a video podcast is a whole
nother ballgame and we probably aren't
gonna do that in the near future our
regular feedback err if this is a valid
English word Miguel Hummer
again asked us two questions one was
that we said that our start and end
States in our mdhd hands on episode have
no name therefore we cannot have a
constraint that all named objects must
have a name that's what he was asking
why is that the case and so the reason
is as follows since we assume that there
is one start in one stop state there's
no point in giving these start and stop
states a name although this is to some
extent obviously an arbitrary decision
so only simple state will extend named
you can't us still have a check that
checks all named elements that they do
have actually a name set however you
cannot have what you cannot have is a
check that assumes that all states are
actually named so we'd have to type this
- named Otto simple state the second
question he asks is why is the
constraint check not included in the
model in my opinion UML supports ocl in
the models wouldn't it be a better place
to keep the constraints directly
attached to the metamodel and therefore
validating the model directly or at
least saying that this is a valid model
or not or that's the separation of the
checks have any other benefits for
example different check files for
different use cases first of all it's
essential that whenever you work with
the models you first check the
constraints technically it doesn't
really matter whether the constraints
are in the metamodel whatever that means
or not for example you can easily
distribute the Ecore file together with
the contrast constraint files in earlier
versions of open architecture where we
had the constraints directly inside the
java metaclasses
and there wasn't operation check
constraints that actually did the checks
and and this operation contained the
checks themselves this was bad since it
was not possible to check different
constraints at different times during
this generator workflow and that really
resulted in significant problems in
several projects of course it would be
nice to add the constraints directly in
the meta modeling tool but EMF doesn't
provide very nice support for that I
would rather enter the constraints into
a text file with a code completing and
syntax highlighting editor than typing
them into a tiny text box with no
context support at all so yes it's
essential that you have a correct set of
constraints but currently I don't see
the two
ready to have them in the metamodel ie
directly in the Ecore file there was
also some feedback from hosts who asked
basically two questions one is I
recently tried to play with open
architecture where 4.0 but was a bit
confused by the documentation as a
beginner who doesn't know about OA
double o IW 3.0 I couldn't easily figure
out whether I should use the classical
or the new 4.0 approach perhaps I give
it another try when following your
episode and looking at the code so my
answer the rule is quite easy although
it might not be stated anywhere that
clearly if you need to use non EMF UML
tools you have to use our W classic as
soon as you want to use EMF and related
tools such as gmf for example you should
use or aw with EMF the other question
from host was how do you test your
template code only by testing the
generated code or also on the meta level
ie do you do test-driven development on
the meta level so typically you only
test your templates by testing the
generated code you'll build a reference
model test model and test the results of
the code generation using normal j-unit
or whatever else unit in some sense
however will also test on the meta level
because constraints are a kind of tests
if I have a model to model
transformation i explicitly tested
independent from the rest of the
workflow using j-unit or constraints
another question from host was whether
it's possible to use open architecture
where only inside eclipse or how well it
can be integrated with and or maven so
it's quite easy you can use it outside
eclipse easily we provide an on task and
also a maven plug-in is currently in the
pipeline and Ray Gonzales from Spain
gave us feedback requesting certain
topics specifically on software
development processes XP u P scrum etc
and yeah we have something in the
pipeline will one or two episodes from
now we'll probably broadcast our
processes episode part 1 and we'll have
a number of additional episodes on
issues he also suggested to get get
Bevan on to our podcast he is the author
of the rife framework which uses
continuations and as it happens actually
was in contact with guilt with regards
to this continuations topic and he gave
us some interesting information about
continuations in java and specifically
in rife and he sent us an mp3 file which
i'll play now hi guys you talked about
continuations and java in your podcast
about the future of enterprise java you
raised many questions about the
applicability of continuations and about
the possibility of doing them in java
our project rife has been mentioned in
that context and you were wondering
about the state of continuations so
continuations are part of the rive
framework which is a web application
framework to allow you to easily express
complex flows control flows in your web
application natively in java the only
thing that you have to do is to insert
pause method calls where you want your
flow to be interrupted and your local
state and program location will be
automatically captured and afterwards at
the next request the execution will
automatically resume where you left off
now I hear you think how is this
possible since Java doesn't support
continuations natively well when your
classes are loaded we automatically
detect if these method calls are present
and then modify the bytecode so that in
parallel we can maintain a method call
stack and a variable stack that will
then be stored by a continuation manager
when that pause method call execute each
continuation has a unique idea and that
ID can then for example be passed as a
query parameter and once it arrives at
the next request the web framework is
able to look up the continuation from
that unique ID
and obtained from the continuation
manager at that point in time the
continuation will be cloned so that you
keep two distinct versions of the
continuations present this allows the
back button for example to work
seamlessly because each individual
continuation step will have a unique ID
now of course to be able to do this the
cloning has to be possible so all the
variables on the stack have to be
cloneable ryf implements a whole number
of default behaviors with regards to
cloning so in most situations you don't
have to do anything as a programmer but
sometimes you might have to implement a
cloneable interface properly if your
classes are too complex another thing to
consider of course is that if you have a
very large local variable state you
might opt to not clone it and to have
each continuation just use the same
state that is possible by setting a
specific configuration flag now another
question that we receive frequently
receive is if this continuation
functionality is only possible within
rive actually it isn't we have started
work to extract this functionality in a
dedicated library and it has as such
already been picked up by for example
web work we are now continuing the
effort of this separate continuations
library and within the next few weeks we
sees we suspect to be able to release a
first stable version of this
additionally we are also working on a
GSR proposal for continuations so that
it might be used in any kind of java
project even not web related thanks a
lot for listening I hope you learned
something about continuations and rive
you can find more information on rifles
org and if you have any additional
questions feel free to hop onto the
mailing list and ask them there so
thanks Garrett for eclair clarifying
that and to all you other listeners if
you want to give
feedback and wanna send us an mp3 that
we can actually play in the podcast
you're you're invited to do so so
instead of sending us texts please send
us an mp3 with at least 128 bit encoding
so we can repeat it or play it in in
decent quality another feedback came
from Bill pew one of the key people who
defined the Java memory model he sent an
email commenting on episode 19 which is
the second concurrency episode where we
erroneously stated that the Java that
the double check locking idiom was
broken and that this was a Java specific
problem this is not true the problem is
not Java specific it is common to all
well basically to all languages but it
is obvious and it's more apparent in
Java because Java has an explicit memory
model other languages don't but it does
not work in C++ for example become
compilers whereas in Java in current
Java versions it is not broken any more
the memory model was fixed so what is at
the heart of this weird thing of double
check locking being broken or not
well the underlying problem is the
common optimization namely the
reordering of processor instructions as
performance optimization as I said it's
very common and while it while we're
inside a single thread it is often
possible to change the execution order
of instructions so that they're executed
in a different order from then thread
which is apparent in the source code as
long as the net result is not it cannot
be seen by other code for example if we
I'm constructing you object color
constructor and assign the newly
constructed object to a pure variable
then it is necessary to first complete
the constructor call and only if the
constructor is finished we assign the
fully initialized object to
variable that is the specified behavior
but as long as we're inside a single
threat of execution arm it is perfectly
okay to first partly first allocate the
memory then partly initialize the object
then assign the memory or the the memory
location of the pointer to the variable
and then finish the initialization that
sort of thing this sort of reordering is
helpful to better fill the internal cues
of proper modern processes it's quite
common but it this leads to problems in
the context of multi-threading as long
as I said as long as we're inside a
single thread of execution it does not
matter because well there's no other
code that could come observe the partly
initialized object through the variable
because the single thread arm well the
next command the next statement in this
single thread of execution is not does
not get control until um the assignment
is finished but if we have another
thread it is possible for the execution
to be interrupted in the middle of the
initialization of the object and if due
to instruction reordering the variable
was assigned a partly initialized object
then not the other thread can
dereference this pointer take a look at
the partly initialized object and this
is bad um it's weird
leads to get errors and this is at the
heart of what of why Bell checked
locking was broken this sort of problem
in the context of multi-threading is is
an old one it's well known hence the key
word volatile was introduced motile is
intended to sort of mean this variable
is well should be accessible from
several threads the most important thing
the most important consequence of that
is that all right accesses to such a
variable go directly to memory arm
other variables are sometimes cashed in
on thread specific memories memory or or
even processor registers but a volatile
variable must always be written right
through to the to the heap memories so
that other threads immediately see the
current state a more subtle other aspect
of aw hell is that processor instruction
reordering must be reduced to such a
degree that other threads will see a
consistent well have a consistent view
of a fully initialized object sort of
which is a vague way of saying this and
it's this is a real really complex thing
the Java memory model the first version
of the Java memory model attempted to
specify this or well it's specified
which reorderings were permitted and
which were not permitted for volatile
variables but there were some special
cases that were not dealt with correctly
in this memory model and this is why um
table check locking was broken there was
a Java specification request as part of
the Java community process jsr 133 which
was finalized in 2004 which defined a
new Java memory model this is where the
PUE did a lot of the work and this meant
that in jdk 1.4 hotspot and jdk 1.5
which is now called j2se 5
wall tile ensures that actually only
such reorderings of instructions are
allowed that really allow other threads
give other threads a consistent view of
the state of variables so double check
blocking works with j2ee 5 now it's a
little stricter but it still permits
some process instruction reorderings
other languages such as C++ for instance
which is the language wear double check
locking originated do not specify an
explicit memory model not as part of the
arm of the language specific
occasion this means that there is no way
to verify or falsify that double check
locking or other idioms of this sort
work or do not work with the language
because the language specification is
too weak too too vague to allow this
sort of proof or disproof but actually
for C++ C or C++ multi-threading
libraries usually just um delegate this
sort of thing or some of the the things
just through to the threading model of
the obligate of the operating system
underneath them and just do some
reorderings and actually well these
reorderings often break things like
double check locking so to summarize we
stand corrected in two issues firstly
double check locking does work with
current Java implementations with a
current Java Virtual Machine based on
the new Java memory model which is part
of the current Java specification and
secondly which is even more important
the problem that we mentioned is not a
Java problem but it is a language
independent problem because this sort of
processor and structure your ordering is
a common optimization of compilers
independently of the language for which
they compile Java has an explicit memory
model that allows us to verify or
disprove that certain idioms work or do
not work other languages do not have
such a memory model but that does not
mean they do not have the problems it
just means that we cannot make any
general say cannot say any general
things about whether they have these
problems or not Gregory gave us feedback
and specifically asked us whether we're
planning to discuss the topic of
documenting the software development
process and also of documentation in
general and something I have to say here
is that we're planning on interviewing a
guy called andreas looping he's the
author of a book called agile
documentation which I personally really
like and this book is about how to write
efficient documentation in projects what
should be documented
how much for which target audience and
he also talks about how to write nice
documents things like layouting and
stuff so we'll have an interview with
him on that topic upcoming there was
more feedback from me he'll hunger and
he specifically asked with regards to
how to organize a model driven software
development project in my or in the MBS
the episodes I kind of suggested to have
separate teams one for developing the
meta artifacts and other teams who would
use those meta artifacts to develop
actual applications and in contrast Eric
Evans in his interview suggested that
the team that built the application
should also be the people who built the
language because building the language
helps understand the problem and
therefore makes the team more productive
so I think the approach I suggested
works really well if you have a number
of similar applications product lines or
in case where there's a complex
technical infrastructure architecture
for which you want to simplify
application development Eric had another
context he wanted to use DSL to enhance
the expressive power of a domain
language here the language is used to
help application developers to express
their potential potentially complex
algorithms here of course it is
essential that those folks who use the
language or also those who created they
create the language to help themselves
express their functionality so I hope
this clarifies the point so this
basically concludes this short feedback
episode again we didn't read all the
emails that said that you know we're
doing great work and there's a great
podcast and we should go on we really
appreciate those emails keep them coming
but probably it's not very interesting
for the listeners to hear all of them
read out loud on the podcast so thanks
for your feedback thanks for listening
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning party for providing the music as
well as lips and comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]